Guide to the Salo W. Baron Papers, 1920-1989 M1162
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Salo Wittmayer Baron papers
1920-1989
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baron, Salo W (Salo Wittmayer), 1895-1989
M1162
10 Linear Feet (19 boxes)
Manuscripts, correspondence, and financial papers of Salo W. Baron, one of the fathers of Jewish Studies. Primarily an artificial collection purchased from a bookdealer and received as a gift.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2000, 2004, and 2011. Gift of Shoshana B. Tancer, 2010. Accessions 2000-260, 2004-075, 2010-234, 2011-175, and 2011-200.
Related Materials
Stanford Special Collections holds another collection of Salo Baron Papers, 1900-1983 (M0580) https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4083818
Jews -- History.; Jewish studies.; Baron, Salo W (Salo Wittmayer), 1895-1989
- Series I. Accession 2000-260
  - Jeanette Baron - Misc Papers (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - SW Baron - Ephemera 1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter re: support for family in Poland (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - to Tobi Baron (SW's brother?) 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Misc Documents (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Two Love Letters (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Professional Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - SW Baron 1970s and 1980s Finances (Personal) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tax Returns 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1934 Wedding Congrats (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Two important Baron checks (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Academic papers (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Misc Baron Envelopes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kohut Foundation Bank Book (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial Report on Conference on Jewish Social Studies 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - YMHA 1935 "Y" Forum - Lectures Poster (including Baron), Baltimore (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters re: Kohut Festschrift (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1930 NY Tax Audit (securities spreadsheets) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Caanan CT Property (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1939 Lawsuit of Polish Bank (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Volume 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Volume 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Volume 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Volume 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Volume 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Volume 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Abbreviations (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Volume VII, pages 0 to 70 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photograph (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bank Books 1935 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bank Books 1936, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bank Book 1946-1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Diary 1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cufflinks, Luggage Tag, Radio Cassette, and "Yifat Shalom" stamp (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Checks 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Checks 1939 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Checks 1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Stock Transactions 1930-1940 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Stock Transactions 1930-1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Checks 1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Checks 1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Check Stub Books 1931-1935 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Checks 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Checks 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Checks 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Checks 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Checks 1933 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Checks 1934 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Checks 1935 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Checks 1935-1936 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Checks 1936 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Checks 1937 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Checks 1938 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Checks 1938 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Accession 2010-234
  - Letters of condolence to Shoshana Baron Tancer on Salo Baron's death, 1989 (Box 11)
  - Letters to and from Baron's parents; correspondence regarding efforts to bring Baron's sister and family to US; household accounts and correspondence; correspondence relating to divorce of Tanya Baron Lindenfeld; correspondence re: estate of Emmanuel Luft; postcards; photocopies, Circa 1930s-1940s (Box 12)
  - Picture postcards, mainly sent to Baron daughters from parents, Circa 1940s (Box 14, Box 13)
  - Postcard sets (Box 14, Box 15)
  - Hebrew Union College honors certificate, presented to Salo Baron on his 90th birthday (Flat-box 16)
  - Accordion file containing stationery; Biblia Hebraica, 1831; plastic ruler from Canaan Savings Bank; Israel souvenirs: brass bookends and 2 olive wood trays (Box 17)
  - Book catalogs (Box 18)
- Series 3: Accession 2011-175
  - Conference of Historians, remarks of Prof. Salo Baron, undated; obituary for M.D. Brandstetter, undated; typescript of German article by Salo Baron, circa 1920s; Judisch und Palastina - Fragenauf dem Zahnten Kongress der Internationalen Union der Volkerbundligen (von Prof. Dr. S. Baron, Wien), 1926.
  - ALS from Arno Erteschik to Baron on the occasion of his wedding, 1934; TLS from David Patterson to Baron re Sacks lecture, 1984; TLS from Ruth L.S. [Hyun?], 1977; Seminar on religion and democracy by Dr. Sal W. Baron, 1947; 10th Sacks lecture (by Prof. Sal Baron), 1983. (Flat-box 19, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Profile of Sal Baron for Polish newspaper, "Chwila," 1930; German clipping on the Jewish Question at the Vienna Congress, c. 1920s; Clipping by Salo Baron, "The Jewish Question at the Vienna Congress." (Flat-box 19, Folder 3)
- Series 4: Accession 2011-200
  - Teshuvah be-safah Italkit me-Avraham Gratsi`ani / Salo Wittmayer Baron, Vienna (Hebrew book, 16 p.; 24 cm.), with manuscript notes, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Wiener Morgenzeitung, 1926 (Box 10, Folders 2-4)
  - Wiener Morgenzeitung, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Juedische Volksstimme, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 6)